A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Vice President for Assets, Office Files of Dr. Melvin L Oliver FA508
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Vice President for Assets, Office Files of Dr. Melvin L Oliver
1982-2009, bulk 1992-2004
1992-2004
Rockefeller Archive Center
Oliver, Melvin L.
Ford Foundation
FA508
3.8 Cubic Feet 10 letter document boxes.
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of a Foundation-wide program reorganization. The new program supported the work of a range of groups and individuals seeking to build the assets and capacities of poor communities through community-based activities, research, policy analysis, and advocacy. In 2009, the Asset Building and Community Development Program became the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program. Dr. Melvin L. Oliver joined the Ford Foundation in 1996. He served as the Foundation's first Vice President for Asset Building and Community Development and worked on issues relating to poverty, community economic development, and reproductive health. The Office Files of Melvin L. Oliver document his professional activities as Vice President of the Assets Program between 1996 and 2009. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence concerning such subjects as ongoing grant activity, potential grantees, and Foundation policy, and briefing books from meetings, conferences, and field visits. A couple of files pertaining to Dr. Oliver's pre-Ford research and writing in Sociology during the 1980s can also be found in the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Melvin L. Oliver was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1950. He received an undergraduate degree from William Penn College in Iowa (1972) and was awarded an M.A. (1974) and a PhD (1977) in Sociology from Washington University in St. Louis. In 1978, he joined the faculty of the University of California Los Angeles, where he worked for the next 17 years. He became known for his work in Sociology, receiving such honors as a fellowship grant from the Ford Foundation in 1982 and the title of "California Professor of the Year" from the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching in 1994.
Dr. Oliver joined the Ford Foundation in 1996. He served as the Foundation's first Vice President for Asset Building and Community Development and worked on issues relating to poverty, community economic development, and reproductive health. In 2004, he returned to academia, accepting an appointment as SAGE Sara Miller McCune Dean of Social Sciences and Professor of Sociology at the University of California Santa Barbara.
Arrangement
Arranged into 3 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Correspondence, 1996-2009
Series II. Meetings, Conferences and Visits, 1991-2004
Series III. Research and Writing, 1982-1988
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Dr. Melvin L. Oliver, a well-known sociologist, document his professional activities between 1982 and 2009. The bulk of files pertain to his tenure as Vice President of the Assets Program at the Ford Foundation.
Separated Materials
A photograph of Dr. Oliver and a fellow Ford Foundation staff member at the Great Wall of China has been transferred to the Trustees and Staff Photo Collection.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of the Foundation-wide program reorganization in the 1997 fiscal year. It took over existing Foundation programs in Urban Poverty, Rural Poverty and Resources, Reproductive Health and Population, and Program-Related Investments. The Assets Program had three program units: Economic Development; Community and Resource Development; and Human Development and Reproductive Health. In 2009, the Asset Building and Community Development Program became the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program.
- Correspondence, 1996-2009; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of Mr. Oliver's incoming and outgoing correspondence and memoranda that Dr. Oliver arranged chronologically by year, and within years, alphabetically by correspondent. Dr. Oliver's separation of external correspondence from internal Ford Foundation memoranda was maintained. Subjects of correspondence include ongoing grant actions, potential grantees, Foundation policy, and other subjects. The files also contain copies of newspaper and magazine articles retained by Dr. Oliver for discussion or reference.
  - Chron File (1 of 18): A-F, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chron File (2 of 18): G-L, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chron File (3 of 18): M-Q, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chron File (4 of 18): S-Z, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chron File (5 of 18): Memoranda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chron File (6 of 18): A-D, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chron File (7 of 18): E-H, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chron File (8 of 18): I-Z, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chron File (9 of 18): Memoranda, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chron File (10 of 18): A-L, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chron File (11 of 18): M-Z, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chron File (12 of 18): Memoranda, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chron File (13 of 18): A-Z, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chron File (14 of 18): Memoranda, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chron File (15 of 18): A-Z, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chron File (16 of 18): Memoranda, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chron File (17 of 18): A-Z, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chron File (18 of 18): A-Z, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - DeGiovanni, Frank -- Correspondence re: PRIs, 1997-2009 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Currently unavailable for research. Requested by Ford Foundation staff 2015.
- Meetings, Conferences and Visits, 1991-2004; II
  As Vice President, Dr. Oliver traveled extensively, visiting grantee locations, attending conferences, and meeting with other Foundation staff members. This series is comprised of the briefing books and other materials he retained from his travels.
  - Poverty and Race Research Action Council (PRRAC) Board Meeting, Washington D.C., Dec 16, 1996 -- Agenda, Notes, Correspondence, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Natural Resources Management Program Officer Consultation, Napa Valley, CA, Jun 9-11, 1996 -- Memoranda, Agenda, Program Descriptions, Notes, Discussion Papers, 1996 April-June (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Asset Program Retreat -- Agenda, Notes, Background, 1996 May 20-July 31 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Community Development Collaborative Partnership Conference -- Agenda, Memoranda, 1996 June (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Development Finance Affinity Group Meeting, Positano, Italy, Nov 4-8, 1996 -- Meeting Book, Memoranda, 1996 September-November (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mexico City Field Office Visit -- Itinerary, Agenda, Meeting Book (1 of 2), 1997 January 2-10 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mexico City Field Office Visit -- Background (2 of 2), 1997 January 2-10 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Madras and New Delhi, India -- Itinerary, Notes, Conference Program, Background Papers (1 of 3), 1997 January 31-February 8 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Madras and New Delhi, India -- Background Papers (2 of 3), 1997 January 31-February 8 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Madras and New Delhi, India -- Ford Program Office Meeting Book (3 of 3), 1997 January 31-February 8 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Trustees Tour of Virginia's Eastern Shore, Northampton County, Virginia, Mar 1997 -- Agenda, Background, Memoranda, Grant Recommendations, 1991-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reproductive Health Worldwide Affinity Group Meeting, Marrakesh, Morocco, Jun 14-19, 1997, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Research Council Conference of Ford Fellows, Washington D.C., Oct 17, 1997, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Natural Resources Affinity Group Meeting, Istanbul, Turkey, Nov 12-16, 1997, 1997 November-December (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Brookings Institution Meeting on Community Development Corporations (CDCs), 1998 January (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Beijing Field Office Visit -- Agenda and Background, 1998 March (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI) Road Trip, May 11-13, 1998 -- Itinerary, Background, Correspondence, 1998 March-July (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Corporation for Enterprise Development (CFED) Ideas in Development Conference, Washington D.C., Jun 24, 1999, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Visit to the World Bank, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Center of Strategic Nonprofit Planning and Community Leadership (NPLC) and National Minority AIDS Council (NMAC) Site Visits, Mar 13, 2001, 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Children's Defense Fund National Symposium on Arts and Scholarship, Clinton, TN, 1999 March 19-21 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - New School University -- Notes, PowerPoint, Email, Conference Information, 1999 April 30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - All Africa Program Officers and Representatives Meeting, Zanzibar (1 of 2), 1999 August 25-September 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - All Africa Program Officers and Representatives Meeting, Zanzibar (2 of 2), 1999 August 25-September 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group Annual Meeting, Bahia, Brazil, 1999 October 9-14 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Ten Point Coalition Visit, Oct 27, 1999, 1999 October 5-November 28 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Development Finance Affinity Group Meeting, London, UK -- Agenda, Notes, PowerPoint, Background, 1999 November 7-10 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Meeting, Jun 27-29, 2000, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Natural Assets Conference -- Agenda, Meeting Book, Background (1 of 2), 2000 January (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Natural Assets Conference -- Meeting Book (2 of 2), 2000 January (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Worldwide Meeting on Youth Involvement, Costa Rica -- Workshop Information (1 of 3), 2000 January 4-7 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Worldwide Meeting on Youth Involvement, Costa Rica -- Country Profiles A-Q (2 of 3), 2000 January 4-7 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Worldwide Meeting on Youth Involvement, Costa Rica -- Country Profiles R-Z (3 of 3), 2000 January 4-7 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Environmental and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) Meeting, Mactan, Philippines -- Agenda Book with Background, Papers, Memoranda (1 of 2), 2000 February 14-18 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Environmental and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) Meeting, Mactan, Philippines -- Itinerary, PowerPoint, Notes, Case Study (2 of 2), 2000 February 14-18 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Moscow Field Office Visit (1 of 2), 2000 March (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Moscow Field Office Visit (2 of 2), 2000 March (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Africa and Middle East Rep RAP, Jerusalem -- Briefing Book, 2000 October 1-6 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Building Broader Women's Health/Reproductive Healthcare Coalitions in the States" (report) by Terry McGovern, 2000 October 24 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chicago/Cleveland Shorebank Site Visits and Cleveland Saves Meeting, 2000 November 30-December 4 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Federation of Southern Cooperative/Land Assistance Fund -- Correspondence and memoranda re: grantee, background, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group Annual Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa, Jan 18-22, 2002, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Vietnam Visit, Jan 8-13, 2001 -- Itinerary, Notes, Memoranda (1 of 3), 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam Visit, Jan 8-13, 2001 -- Briefing Book (2 of 3), 2001 January 8-13 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam Visit, Jan 8-13, 2001 -- Briefing Book (3 of 3), 2001 January 8-13 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Youth Service Workshop, Costa Rica, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Cairo Field Office Visit, 2001 March (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Environmental and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa, Jan 21-25, 2002 -- Program, Schedule, Notes, Email, 2001 October 18-2002 January 21 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Reflections on The Ford Foundation's Role in Building a Global Field of Development Finance and Economic Security" (separated report) by Frank F. DeGiovanni, 2002 February 20 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Affinity Group on Development Finance and Economic Security Meeting, Beijing, China -- Meeting Book, Agenda, Reports, Background, 2002 February 26-March 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Visit to Mexico -- Meeting Book, Agenda, RGAs, 2002 May 11-19 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Latin America Regional Program -- Annotated Agenda, Background, 2002 October (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Asia Representatives' Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- Meeting Book, 2002 December 9-11 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - All Africa Program Staff Meeting, Sep 17-20, 2002 -- Agenda, Objectives, Background, Briefing Book, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Corporate Involvement Initiative (CII) Convening, Jun 2-4, 2003 -- Correspondence, Agenda, Background, 2003 March 24-June 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Special Initiative on Africa: Senegal (1 of 2), 2004 August (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Special Initiative on Africa: Senegal (2 of 2), 2004 August (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Research and Writing, 1982-1988; III
  This series consists of two folders. Both pre-date Dr. Oliver's tenure at the Foundation. One contains information retained by Dr. Oliver about his Ford Foundation-funded postdoctoral fellowship administered by the National Science Foundation. The other is an undated paper from the early 1980s containing Dr. Oliver's views on affirmative action.
  - "Is Affirmative Action Necessary? One Sociologist's Viewpoint" by Melvin L. Oliver, early 1980s (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - National Science Foundation Postdoctoral Fellowship, 1982-1988 (Box 10, Folder 5)